In the previous video, we saw the first type of network, which was the private network.
But if you or your team don't have enough knowledge about the technology or if you just don't want to
build a private network because it's not relevant, then you can ask the service to a public operator.
The LoRaWANoperator will give us the network coverage.
It has a high number of gateways spread all over the country and those gateways are all configured to
send their data to an operator network server.
And that's great because we'll also have access to this network server.
So the server infrastructure is also provided.
So in the case of a public network, everything is owned by the operator except your own device.
However, there are two drawbacks that we can notice if you use a public network.
First, if you have a large number of devices, then the subscription will be expensive.
And secondly, even if we deploy devices where it's supposed to be covered by the network, we'll always
find a situation where it doesn't work.
It can be because your device is in a basement or behind big concrete walls.
But because you use a public network and you can't assign yourself a specific location for the gateways,
then there is nothing much you can do about this situation.
Now, I'm sure you want to know how much is it for a subscription?
Well, that depends on the number of uplink messages you will be able to send per days.
And that also depends on the number of downlink messages.
Because downlink flows in lorawan is very limited.
So you will probably be charged more if you use a lot of downlink data.
Anyway, it's roughly around €1.5 per month and per device.
And if you want to know which public operator is available in your country, then you can go on the
alliance website.
And select the country you're interested in.
In France, for example, there are two public operators available right now.